Anne Porter Papers
Manuscript Division, Library of Congress
Anne Porter Papers 1911-2014 (bulk 1931-2006)
MSS85991
Porter, Anne, 1911-2011.
1,200 items
5 containers
1.8 linear feet
Manuscript Division, Library of Congress Washington, D.C.
Poet. Correspondence, poems, notebooks, photographs, articles, legal papers, and other miscellany documenting Porter's life and career as a poet.
Selected Search Terms
The following terms have been used to index the description of this collection in the LC Catalog. They are grouped by name of person or organization, by subject or location, and by occupation and listed alphabetically.
People
Porter family--Correspondence.; Porter family.; Porter, Anne, 1911-2011--Friends and associates.; Porter, Anne, 1911-2011.; Porter, Fairfield--Correspondence.; Porter, Laurence M., 1936- --Correspondence.
Organizations
New York School of poets and painters.
Subjects
American poetry.; Art--Societies, etc.; Artists--New York (State)--New York.; Christian poetry, American.; Christianity.; Faith.; Nature.; Poetry--Societies, etc.; Poetry.; Poets, American--New York (State)--New York.
Places
New York (N.Y.)--Intellectual life--20th century.
Occupations
Poets.
Provenance
The papers of Anne Porter, poet, were given to the Library of Congress in 2011 by Porter. Additions were given from 2013 to 2016 by the estate of Anne Porter.
Transfers
Audiovisual material including Rudy Burckhardt's film A Day in the Life of a Cleaning Woman and one sound recording has been transferred to the Motion Picture, Broadcasting, and Recorded Sound Division where it is identified as part of the Anne Porter Papers.
Access and Restrictions
Restrictions apply governing the use, photoduplication, or publication of items in this collection. Consult reference staff in the Manuscript Division for information concerning these restrictions. In addition, many collections are stored off-site and advance notice is needed to retrieve these items for research use.
Biographical Note
Date Event
1911, Nov. 6 Born, Sherborn, Mass.
1932 Married Fairfield Porter (died 1975)
1934 1938 Published poems in Poetry
1949 Moved to Southampton, N.Y.
1953 Starred in Rudy Burckhardt's film A Day in the Life of a Cleaning Woman
1954 Converted to Catholicism
1979 2000 Published poems in Commonweal
1994 Published An All Together Different Language, Poems 1938-1994. Cambridge, Mass.: Zoland Books Nominated for National Book Award for Poetry
2006 Published Living Things: Collected Poems. Hanover, N.H.: Zoland Books
2011, Oct. 10 Died, Hampton Bays, N.Y.
Scope and Content Note
The papers of Anne Porter (1911-2011) span the years 1911-2014, with the bulk of the material concentrated in the period 1931-2006. Correpondence, poems, notebooks, photographs, articles, legal papers, and other miscellany pertain chiefly to the life and career of Porter. The papers are in English. The collection is arranged alphabetically by topic or type of material and therein chronologically or alphabetically.
The papers primarily consist of Porter's correspondence and poems that were assembled and inventoried by her son, Laurence M. Porter. Correspondents include Laurence M. Porter, Fairfield Porter, Katharine Minot Channing, and other Porter family members. Topics include family, friends, faith, poetry, and members of the New York School of poets and painters.
Porter published a few poems in the 1930s, and after the death of her husband, artist Fairfield Porter, she again began publishing poems in journals and books. The papers include drafts and copies of published and unpublished poems on loose pages and in notebooks. Porter's love of nature and Christian faith permeate the poems, and several include variant drafts with edits. Many of the poems appeared in Porter's books An Altogether Different Language, Poems 1938-1994 and Living Things: Collected Poems. Articles in the collection document Porter's career and nomination for the National Book Award for Poetry in 1994.
Arrangement of the Papers
This collection is arranged alphabetically by topic or type of material and therein chronologically or alphabetically.
Container List
- Articles and reviews, 1994-1999, 2006, undated (Box 1)
- Certificates, 1911, 1932, 2005, 2011 (Box 1)
- Correspondence (Box 1)
  - Family (Box 1)
    - Channing, Katharine Minot (mother), 1932-1934, 1949-1954, 1960-1961, (2 folders) (Box 1)
    - Porter, Laurence M. (son) (Box 1)
      - From Anne Porter, 1955-2010, (4 folders); (1 folder) (Box 1, Box 2)
      - To Anne Porter, 1976-2009, (2 folders) (Box 2)
      - To Anne Porter and Fairfield Porter, 1944-1975, (2 folders) (Box 2)
  - General, 1955, 1961-1984, 1991-2013, undated (Box 2)
- Interview transcript, 2009-2010 (Box 2)
- Legal papers, 1976-1978, 1993-2006 (Box 2)
- Miscellany, 1994, 2001, 2010-2012, undated (Box 3)
- Notebooks, undated, (3 folders); (1 folder) (Box 3, Box 4)
- Photographs, 1913, 1927, 1934, 1945, 1960, 1983, 1994, 2005, undated (Box 4)
- Poetry, 1934-1938, 1954, 1961, 1978-2000, 2006-2014, undated, (5 folders) (Box 4)
- Porter, Fairfield (husband), 1931-1960, 1993-2005, (3 folders) (Box 5)
- Porter, Johnny (son), 1934-1952 (Box 5)
- Steerforth Press and Zooland Books, 1993, 2001-2005 (Box 5)